hi welcome back to lamrim uh good
morning
or something else uh we're gonna start
today
with a meditation and about
average three hours a day four hours a
day something
and uh
when and it's very beautiful
and i i can remember being in a debate
and
orion rose over my opponent's head and
it was very beautiful
and this
boohoo is it's the source of the english
verb to be and
when you add it
it means to make you into something the
anna is
an er in english
it means the person who does something
so music
is
that's that is the word for meditator so
it's not
i don't know where meditate comes from
maybe reach a medium state or something
[Music]
i haven't taught it for many years we
taught
means you burn a pathway into your mind
so you you take a new series of ideas
like a road map uh like we have a map
with the gps to
[Music]
so on the gps
you get a gpa
right oh we're going to take it
strawberry
okay it's just that gail said makes
really good coffee
okay uh so
each piece of the road map you get it
and that's how we're taught to meditate
uh
and here's how to go to payson and
here's how to go to
what's the other one pine and then
here's how to get the strawberry
and then uh
learn
over and over again
um
and when it burns itself into your mind
and you can close your eyes and go
through the whole meditation
and that's what norm is in this case you
would
you don't have tonight the different
methods of reaching body today
each other
and those are uh we use them in the
monastery those are
memory uh
[Music]
you
you experienced already in your life
okay
like when i memorized the i memorized
the first three chapters of
[Music]
something that happened previously in
your life okay and
a series of ideas into your mind
and it's based on mnemonics so you you
have to
and that meant a lot to you i'm thinking
like having your children or something
and you probably remember a lot of the
details and
um
this happened the water broke then we
ran around and then we decided not to
[Music]
don't miss anything and and then slowly
that gets burned into your mind until it
becomes you
what do i do what's it leave a dumb
dummy
so we're gonna try it for bodhichitta
okay so here we go
so and it's fantastic when you're
teaching
okay
[Music]
um
i hate to say benefits 10 cool things
[Music]
so i'm using mnemonics okay
and
or maybe not you do okay first picture
it was tennis player
[Music]
um
second picture was at graduation right
now
skyscraper makers and that was the whole
class that was the first
of the first class and if i want to
meditate on the first class
and burn it into my mind and then become
that
man
[Music]
i connected uh events to i connected
parts of the high school to
to the first class that i taught
yesterday okay so
i don't get annoyed because i was on the
tennis team
me
future farmers of america where they
used to keep their animals
that's where the donkey was waiting for
me
okay
okay like your high school probably
didn't look like my high school
and then you become an extraordinary
teacher also because you don't have
so as usual we'll try to
relax your face relax
relax your eyelids
to push down which
forces your chest and head up
uh but it got bit
[Music]
the way you do that is on your exhales
you can use your exhales as an
excuse to tighten your lower abdomen
and that tightens here
[Music]
and you can sit up straight you can
meditate longer
when you write tables
let's take ten deep breaths in the
exhales
[Music]
so at the end of the exhale your tummy
tightens
which strengthens your back
[Music]
just park them
i don't mind the sun it's good
now let's go through our five pictures
[Music]
and i'm gonna start on the tennis courts
who's happy because he just got a
position on the tennis team
[Music]
benefit
extraordinary beings who have had the
experience of
leaping from planet to planet
and meeting
[Music]
a special team
meditation into my mind
[Music]
how would that feel
next go to a place
that you remember that will remind you
of the graduation
[Music]
no the beings
in the universe who are
extraordinary um
that's all that bodhisattva
[Music]
oh
on each part of the
path that i'd like to burn into my mind
[Music]
the next idea we learned was that you
get a second title
[Music]
of a father or mother buddha
coming to give me a hug
[Music]
um
once you have jumped between
planets
to help them directly to them
[Music]
feeling for you uh
then in my high school picture i i go
from the
football field where my mom and dad
hugged me
after graduation
[Music]
um
uh or moral geniuses to become a
bodhisattva
we don't have to be the smartest person
that's inside thank
we have lots of weaknesses
we have addictions that we have
[Music]
but still we can become a body supper
the text said even a donkey or a fish
[Music]
great intellectual quality someone
who's a normal
[Music]
even in our practice but
still that path is available to us
[Music]
okay
then the last picture for me at my high
school is i go to the
gymnasium and they build an extra
top on the side of on outside the
gymnasium
[Music]
from
it seemed like a whole building was
moving
shaking actually jumping from side to
side
and
that reminds me of what happens when any
person
jumps from planet to planet and reaches
becomes a body sufferer
[Music]
and if my relationship with every living
being
changes suddenly then
that
karma that created the galaxy
and the galaxy jumps
and trembles from the weight of this
new kind of love that i found
[Music]
then the galaxy has to
jump when i do
well
[Music]
all people keep
that one of the one of us in the
galaxy just became a bodhisattva
[Music]
um
trouble
[Music]
could become a body supper um
and then slowly open your eyes
any questions about anybody here
in the room small questions
my question is when the earth shifted
for you
was that you're becoming a bodhisattva
or some other
[Music]
yeah if i felt the earth shift
under under me did that mean i became a
body staff
or did that mean that
[Music]
[Laughter]
video
if it happens no no
[Music]
uh
you you'll you'll know and you'll be
very happy
how's
let's get to work enough fun
by the way
you can only do about five scenes
at a time like don't try to do 10 don't
try to do 20.
do do five pictures well
or some event in your life and do the
five well and the next day
you know
[Music]
and we're going to cover many other
pictures and you you won't have time to
do all of them
so don't get uh frantic
[Music]
pictures when you do the second five
pictures
uh and then you'll feel frustrated you
feel like oh i'm not making progress
i've already forgotten my pictures
and don't think like that okay
um
finger
[Music]
here we go
hos right that's right that's right
okay
[Music]
is an interesting
that
okay like how many teachings did lord
give
we have nine times
books uh in john brady's database
spoken by lord buddha uh but that's a
that's about it
um
[Music]
one opinion is that it's the amount that
a magical
elephant could carry called
that's a big story long story but uh
anyway he says if you wanted to like
identify moons in
the
it's nothing other than what i just
taught you
it's the five scenes at your high school
okay it's to be a bodhisattva okay
choose one teaching
um
[Music]
who can guess
now 20 bucks
can't okay don't forget
i was going to say 20 bucks i just
didn't have time uh
yeah fat chick means the one
divine being so sometimes after is
called
um
which we're going to talk
just focus on that don't get distracted
by anything else just do that
okay
[Music]
it's important okay
says give up on this life
and i remember
we were in new jersey
and there was a
like a few acres of of woodlands
swampy woodlands across the street
okay and uh this is called freewood
acres in new jersey
the rest is all gasoline refineries but
uh
there was this one little probably
polluted
[Music]
give up on this life and he packed up
his house and he moved across the street
into the forest and uh
he lasted about two days and
ripped it was so funny he just said
leave him you know he'll come
he'll be back in a day or two the guy
struggled back after two days he said i
need a house
i need a bed refrigerator
it doesn't mean um
and look guess what
sometimes go good and sometimes
it's gonna go messy allocating
it sometimes it's gonna be very
fun and then something okay that's a
regular voice
just relax okay
you know you try to raise money for
stupa you have a mess and been teaching
then suddenly i was confused upset
and you're like okay just relax okay
whatever happens in your project that
the ghost things go well things don't go
well
the only thing that matters is do you
love the other people in the project
that's all that matters okay um
[Music]
the project makes money and there's a
big stupid
give up this idea uh success means
the people in the project are
feeling deep love for each other
we have reached the fourth benefit who
can tell me the first three
and that one importantly includes a hug
from your parents
and then with the third one oh this is
the encouragement
no no we only covered the first two
benefits in the five pictures
[Music]
good yeah outshining silky number okay
uh i'm sorry uh a body suffer
outshines millions of nice people
okay nice people are nice but a
bodhisattva i'm sorry it's just
different it's a different level they're
jumping from planet to planet
directly helping billions of people
well
and it's more efficient if you could
reach that
you could never go down
the english
[Music]
uh
uh and
what's this picture represent so burn it
into your mind
if you do become a body thoughtful this
is something you bring to the time
um
uh it's gonna take him to buddha
paradise for a hundred lifetimes
and you can't listen
oh thanks for giving me a hundred
dollars now you're going to go to buddha
paradise for a thousand lifetimes
but the fact is
tiny little things that people do for
you you can have the
pleasure of knowing that little things
that people
do for you are gonna cause them intense
lifetimes of happiness
just because of who you are
[Music]
the pleasure that because you're a
bodhisattva
when somebody else helps you or
even somebody puts gas in your car or
something
that they're gonna go to some paradise
for
lifetimes because they did something for
you
because you are you've you have had the
experience of helping billions of people
so you're a heavy crime you're much
heavier coming object than their parents
or anything like that
because it helps them
screw you or something and then you just
find a way to turn it into a nice
interaction
and then it helps them and it's really
fun
somebody tries
to
um intense good karma
so it's nice to be that kind of a
special
karmic object anonymously right you
don't tell us
[Music]
who create your internet or your roads
or
strange people you can rejoice in
strange
what do you call it
[Music]
because they're making such good karma
you see what i mean
state of mind
you become someone who is worthy of the
of the people should show themselves on
the floor
around you it would
[Music]
okay marvel comics
should be throwing themselves on the
floor okay
what okay fifty dollars worthy of
frustration sounds good
word worthy
come on
[Music]
okay all right
okay
[Music]
okay next picture
you guys look at detail now
by the way now you see why i like to use
pictures because i use them for my
meditation
and then i use them as meditation
and
um
know anybody outside of arizona nobody
and i got off the plane and uh
i went i went and asked someone how do i
get to princeton from
john f kennedy airport they said you
have to take a private plane
they cheated me you actually take a bus
and uh i took a private plane
it cost me like you know nowadays it'd
be like two thousand
you know i lost half my money the first
day and then
and i showed up in a suit in a green
suit that my mother said
everybody at princeton would wear and
everyone was dressed in
tie-dye and they had long hair and it
was the hippie times
and i like took the suit off in like
five minutes
you know and then i i remember i went to
sign up
to my room you know and uh
i got an assignment to a room they said
you're staying with three other people
you know you know sweet and i said okay
you know when i went there and i knock
on the door and these three beautiful
girls come out
and i like is this my room
they said no no you can't stay here
[Music]
and but i never forgot the professional
diver
thing
[Music]
he starts to talk about
how much hard work and discipline
it takes to have the body softness
experience
um
[Music]
you know look it's fun to jump from
planet to planet
it's fun to be the kind of person when
someone offers you
a level
that's all beautiful stuff but okay
new thing
i don't want this hard work
[Music]
they used to say the reason
people are practicing tantra
diamond ring with a special buddha
um
now of course it's an exaggeration okay
of course it's an exaggeration that's
what teachers do
so the early buddhists used to say
why is this guy spending all his time on
some
secret uh tantric buddha
or some mantras and they said well it's
easy to explain he didn't have anything
to maintain
so they gave him that you see so he
didn't have a practice
so they're criticizing that
the latest
and it takes a lot of hard work it's
like being an olympic
level athlete you know it takes
hours
[Music]
again
and he says every chance you get
back to hear a little bit more from
about
the bodhisattva every chance you get
thank
[Music]
or waiting until the class is over wait
until the class is over
even if you're uncomfortable because
during that
time you might miss some seats
anything you ever experienced has an
indelible effect on you
at some point so try to moisturize
[Music]
every little thing you expose your mind
to
in the dharma every sentence from the
alarm ring
every time you do another mantra you
are planting
somebody asked me i don't know
if
a little bit better of course you're
planning to
very powerful sin extremely preferences
okay
um
500 ducks
flying over the buddha when he was
giving a
teaching one time and they heard his
voice
you know in the in a temporary paradise
and they all saw emptiness after that
okay
because they didn't go to the bathroom
during the class
they heard that one more sentence
seeds in their minds so he says you know
something more take it without getting
nervous then what do you call that
hey i if you be in the class it's better
you lay down than you not be in the
class
okay and you're here
come on
[Music]